In the last few videos, we
在最后几个视频中，(字幕翻译：中国海洋大学，周丽雅)
talked about a collaborative filtering algorithm.
我们讨论一个协同过滤算法。
In this video I'm going to
在这个视频中，我将
say a little bit about the
介绍一下这个算法的
vectorization implementation of this algorithm.
向量化实现，
And also talk a little bit about other things you can do with this algorithm.
另外再介绍一下你使用这个算法可以实现的一些功能。
For example, one of the
比如说，你可以用这个算法实现：
things you can do is, given
给定一个商品，
one product can you find
你可以找到
other products that are related
与之相关的其他商品。
to this so that for
比如说：
example, a user has recently been looking at one product.
一个用户最近一直在寻找一个商品
Are there other related products
有没有一些相关的其他商品
that you could recommend to this user?
你能推荐给这个用户？
So let's see what we could do about that.
所以针对这样的问题一起看一下我们如何解决
What I'd like to do is work
我希望可以
out an alternative way of
找到另一种方法
writing out the predictions of the collaborative filtering algorithm.
写出协同过滤算法的预测值
To start, here is our
首先，这是我们的数据集，
data set with our
数据集中包含
five movies and what I'm
五部电影，下一步
going to do is take
我要做的是
all the ratings by all the
得到所有用户对所有电影的评分
users and group them into
然后把它们分组写入矩阵
a matrix. So, here we have
这里我们有五部电影、
five movies and four
四个用户，
users, and so this
因此
matrix y is going to be
这个矩阵y是5行4列的矩阵。
a 5 by 4 matrix. It's just you know, taking all
正如你所知，构成矩阵时，要包括所有的元素，
of the elements, all of this data.
和所有的数据，
Including question marks, and grouping them into this matrix.
包括问号，然后把它们按组写入矩阵。
And of course the elements of this
当然，这个矩阵的
matrix of the (i, j) element of
第(i, j)个元素
this matrix is really what
就是
we were previously writing as y
我们之前说的y（i,j）
superscript i, j. It's
其中ij是上标。它是
the rating given to movie i
第j个用户给第i部电影的评分。
by user j. Given this
给定矩阵y
matrix y of all the
y包含所有我们已知的评分，
ratings that we have, there's
有
an alternative way of writing
另一种方法可以写出
out all the predictive ratings of the algorithm.
这个算法的所有预测评分。
And, in particular if you
尤其是如果你想
look at what a certain
查看某一个用户
user predicts on a
对某一个电影的评分预测
certain movie, what user j
用户j
predicts on movie i is given by this formula.
对电影i的评分预测由这个公式给出（θ(j)的转置乘以x(i)）
And so, if you have
因此，如果你
a matrix of the predicted
有一个预测评分的矩阵
ratings, what you would
你所拥有的
have is the following
就是下面这个矩阵,
matrix where the i, j entry.
矩阵元素的标号为i,j
So this corresponds to the rating
这对应了我们预测的
that we predict using j
用户j给电影i的打分
will give to movie i
is exactly equal to that
这与
theta j transpose
theta j 转置乘以xi的值相等。
XI, and so, you know, this is a matrix
因此，这个矩阵中
where this first element
第一个元素
the one-one element is a
即第一行第一列的元素
predictive rating of user one
是用户一对
or movie one and this
电影一的评分预测
element, this is the one-two
这是第一行第二个元素
element is the predicted rating
它是第二个用户
of user two on movie
对第一部电影的评分预测，
one, and so on,
以此类推。
and this is the
这是
predicted rating of user one
第一个用户
on the last movie and
对最后一部电影的评分预测。
if you want, you know,
如果你要预测，
this rating is what we
则这个评分就是
would have predicted for this value
对这个值的预测；
and this rating is
这个评分就是
what we would have predicted for that
对这个值的预测，
value, and so on.
以此类推。
Now, given this matrix of
现在，给定这个预测评分矩阵
Predictive ratings there is then
则有一个
a simpler or vectorized way of writing these out.
比较简单的或者向量化的方法来写出它们。
In particular if I define
比如说，如果我定义
the matrix x, and this
矩阵x,它
is going to be just
可以写成
like the matrix we had earlier for linear regression to be
像之前讲过的线性回归的矩阵形式
sort of x1 transpose x2
第一行是x1的转置
transpose down to
然后第二行是x2的转置
x of nm transpose.
一直到xnm的转置
So I'm take all the features
我将提取所有的电影的特征
for my movies and stack
然后逐行的
them in rows.
写入矩阵中。
So if you think of
所以如果将
each movie as one example
每部电影看作一个样本
and stack all of the features
将不同电影的所有属性都
of the different movies and rows.
按行写入矩阵
And if we also to
如果我们
find a matrix capital theta,
找到一个矩阵，用大写的theta 表示
and what I'm going to
我要做的是
do is take each of
取出每个
the per user parameter
用户参数向量
vectors, and stack them in rows, like so.
像这样按行写入
So that's theta 1, which
这是theta 1
is the parameter vector for the first user.
是对第一个用户的参数向量
And, you know, theta 2, and
theta 2
so, you must stack
你必须像这样
them in rows like this to
按行把它们写入
define a matrix capital
来定义矩阵大写theta
theta and so I have
因此我有
nu parameter vectors all stacked in rows like this.
nu 个参数向量，像这样按行写入矩阵
Now given this definition
现在给定这个
for the matrix x and this
对矩阵x的定义，和
definition for the matrix theta
这个对矩阵theta的定义
in order to have a
为了获得
vectorized way of computing the
一个向量化方法来计算
matrix of all the predictions
预测矩阵，
you can just compute x times
你可以只是计算x乘以
the matrix theta transpose, and
矩阵theta 的转置，
that gives you a vectorized way
它就是一个向量化的方法
of computing this matrix over here.
来计算这个矩阵，
To give the collaborative filtering
这个协同过滤算法
algorithm that you've been using another name.
有另一个名字，
The algorithm that we're using
我们正使用的这个算法
is also called low rank
也叫低秩
matrix factorization.
矩阵分解
And so if you hear
因此如果你听到
people talk about low rank matrix
人们谈论低秩矩阵
factorization that's essentially exactly
分解，基本上他们所说的就是
the algorithm that we have been talking about.
我们正在讨论的这个算法。
And this term comes from the
这个术语来自于：
property that this matrix
这个矩阵的数学性质；
x times theta transpose has a
矩阵x乘以theta 的转置
mathematical property in linear
在线性代数中有一个数学性质
algebra called that this
称为
is a low rank matrix and
低秩矩阵
so that's what gives
这就是为什么算法
rise to this name low
起名叫
rank matrix factorization for these
低秩矩阵分解的原因。
algorithms, because of this low
因为
rank property of this matrix x theta transpose.
矩阵x乘以theta 的转置的低秩性质。
In case you don't know what
如果你不知道什么
low rank means or in case you don't
是低秩，或者如果你不知道
know what a low rank matrix is, don't worry about it.
一个低秩矩阵是什么，不要紧，
You really don't need to know that in order to use this algorithm.
如果只是为了使用这个算法，你不需要知道那些知识。
But if you're an expert in
但是如果你是一个线性代数领域的专家，或了解线性代数
linear algebra, that's what gives
那是为什么这个算法
this algorithm, this other name
又有另一个名字
of low rank matrix factorization.
低秩矩阵分解的原因
Finally, having run the
最后，在已经运行了
collaborative filtering algorithm here's
协同过滤算法之后
something else that you can do
再讲一个问题，
which is use the learned
利用已经学习到的属性
features in order to find related movies.
来找到相关的电影。
Specifically for each product i
具体的说，就是对每个商品i,
really for each movie i, we've
比如对每个电影i，我们已经
learned a feature vector xi.
学到一个属性向量xi,
So, you know, when you learn a
当你学习某一组特征时，
certain features without really know
你之前并不知道
that can the advance what the
该选取哪些
different features are going to be, but if you
不同的特征，但是如果你
run the algorithm and perfectly the features
运行这个算法，一些特征
will tend to capture what are
将捕捉到
the important aspects of these
different movies or different products or what have you.
不同电影或不同商品的重要的方面。
What are the important aspects that cause
这些重要的方面将导致
some users to like certain
一些用户喜欢某些
movies and cause some users
电影，导致一些用户
to like different sets of movies.
喜欢另外一些电影。
So maybe you end up
可能你最终
learning a feature, you know, where x1
学习一个特征，比如x1
equals romance, x2 equals
代表浪漫爱情，x2代表
action similar to
动作片
an earlier video and maybe you
也许你
learned a different feature x3 which
学到另一个不同的属性x3，
is a degree to which this is a comedy.
描述电影的喜剧效果
Then some feature x4 which is, you know, some other thing.
特征x4可能代表其他的特征。
And you have N
这样你总共有N
features all together and after
个特征，在你
you have learned features it's actually often
学习完特征之后，实际上
pretty difficult to go in
很难理解
to the learned features and come
这些被学习到的特征
up with a human understandable
并对这些特征给出人类可以理解的解释。
interpretation of what these features really are.
But in practice, you know, the
但是，实际上，
features even though these features can be hard to visualize.
即使这些特征难以可视化，
It can be hard to figure out just what these features are.
人们难以理解这些特征的含义，
Usually, it will learn
但是，通常，算法将学到一些重要
features that are very meaningful
特征，这些特征非常有意义，
for capturing whatever are the
它们捕捉到一部电影的
most important or the most salient
最重要的特征
properties of a movie
that causes you to like or dislike it.
这些特征导致了你喜欢或不喜欢这部电影。
And so now let's say we want to address the following problem.
现在再看下一个问题：
Say you have some specific movie
比如你有一部电影
i and you want
i,你想要
to find other movies j
找到另一部电影j
that are related to that movie.
它与电影i相关。
And so well, why would you want to do this?
为什么你要这样做呢？
Right, maybe you have a
好的，假设你有一个用户
user that's browsing movies, and they're
正在浏览电影，他们
currently watching movie j, than
当前正在看电影j，
what's a reasonable movie to recommend
那么在他们看完电影j后，
to them to watch after they're done with movie j?
推荐给他们哪一部电影比较合理呢？
Or if someone's recently purchased movie
或者如果有人最近买了电影j的碟片，
j, well, what's a different
movie that would be reasonable to recommend to them for them to consider purchasing.
那么向他们再推荐哪部电影更合理呢？
So, now that you have
现在，既然你已经
learned these feature vectors, this gives
学习到了这些特征向量，这给了
us a very convenient way to
我们一种方便的方法去
measure how similar two movies are.
衡量两个电影的相似度。
In particular, movie i
举例说，电影i
has a feature vector xi.
有一个特征向量xi,
and so if you can find
如果你找到
a different movie, j, so
一个另一个电影j,
that the distance between
xi和xj的距离很小，
xi and xj is small,
then this is a pretty
那么，这就表明
strong indication that, you know, movies
j and i are somehow similar.
电影j和i相似，
At least in the sense that some of them
至少从这个意义上说，
likes movie i, maybe more likely to like movie j as well.
一些喜欢电影i的人也可能喜欢电影j.
So, just to recap, if
现在，简要的回顾一下，如果
your user is looking
你的用户正在看
at some movie i and if
某个电影i，如果
you want to find the 5
你想要找到5个
most similar movies to that
与电影i最相似的电影
movie in order to recommend
目的是推荐
5 new movies to them, what
五部新电影给用户，你要做的是
you do is find the five
找到5部电影j,
movies j, with the
smallest distance between the
这些电影的特征向量与电影i的特征向量
features between these different movies.
有最小的距离。
And this could give you a few different movies to recommend to your user.
这样你就能够向你的用户推荐几部不同的电影了。
So with that, hopefully, you
希望通过以上的学习，你
now know how to use
现在知道如何使用
a vectorized implementation to compute
一个向量化的实现来计算
all the predicted ratings of
所有用户对所有电影的
all the users and all the
评分预测值。
movies, and also how to do
也可以实现
things like use learned features
利用已经学习到的特征
to find what might be movies
来找到彼此
and what might be products that aren't related to each other.
（不？）相关的电影或商品。